I'm trying to derisk my effort slashin
increase my hit rate. So I was like, how
do I use data but not make myself a
clone that's copy pasting everyone
else's stuff. And that's basically why I
built Sand Castle's movie. That's
Callaway. He started four businesses
that were all killed by the same
problem. No one cared. He had no
audience, which meant he had no
customers. So he made it his mission to
crack audience growth. and now he has
over a billion views, a 50% viral hit
rate, and he created a tool called Sand
Castles that helps other creators do the
same. In this episode, you'll learn the
exact system he uses to find and
validate viral video topics before he
ever hits record.
>> My framework for content is I call it
the modern content stack.
>> The metrics you need to obsess over so
that your content grows your business.
>> Views are not the right metric to study.
Use our A metric to study and I would
say the third most important when I look
at the stack.
>> And if you stick around long enough,
Callaway will show you exactly how you
can build your own content research
system from scratch. Thank you to one of
10 for sponsoring this video.
>> There's kind of a fallacy between like
views equals money. It's really like
views does not equal money. You want
density around one ICP as many times as
you can possibly get it in a given week.
So like my framework on this is called
content minutes. So essentially like you
could imagine your offer ladder or
whatever your offer stack at certain
price points. So I don't know what
you're like running right now, but I
know you have the lab which is probably
one of your higher ticket things. And
then as you go down you've got like
course bundles, individual courses.
Maybe you have something at $47. So
essentially like imagine you took that
ladder from low to high and you overlaid
an amount of minutes that someone would
have to watch your content and trust you
for those minutes. That's like pretty
critical. And at the $47, maybe it's
like 20 minutes worth of content. And at
20 minutes, they'd trust you enough to
buy it if it fit their problem. And then
one one rung upg
like to get into the lab, they probably
would have to have watched hundreds of
minutes. But like once they cross that
threshold, then they'll convert. So if
you think about it, most people are
like, "Well, I should just do YouTube."
Because every YouTube video, if it's 20,
and yours or podcasts, like 60 minutes
long, the average watch time, let's say,
is 20 to 30 minutes. You're getting a
lot of those blocks in one shot. And so
you can scale someone up that ladder of
trust pretty quick, which is why you've
had so much success with YouTube, right?
Because somebody watches five episodes,
that might happen in a single night.
Boom, you hit 200 minutes, and then
they'll they'll be willing to buy
anything. My framework for content is I
call it the modern content stack, which
is a basically a triangle. You've got
short form, long form, both going into
email. That's like the golden goose. If
you if you could do anything, it would
be one short form platform. I think
Instagram is the most valuable or
LinkedIn depending on the audience. for
you is probably Instagram, YouTube for
long form, both into email and you you
pretty much can't lose. Now, from a
content man perspective, you may think
if I had to make a tradeoff of YouTube
verse short form, you're going to want
YouTube. And I agree with that, right?
The reason most people want to start
with short form is because YouTube's so
difficult, like so many moving parts,
you've already cracked it. However, once
you're getting what you're getting from
YouTube and you kind of have a formula,
that's when you look to expand the
universe into short form to kind of get
more uh breadth of the minutes to bring
it all back to what I was starting with
in terms of the narrow ICP. The minutes
don't acrue unless the person who
watched the video trust you and actually
have the problem you're talking about.
So if you broadened or you know made
more generic the topic you're talking
about yeah maybe it gets 100,000 views
instead of 20 but actually none of those
100,000 blocks hit because no trust was
acred because the topic you had to talk
about was so generic and like surface
level that it didn't actually acrue
trust. So for me it's like what I try to
get people to do is very narrowly define
your ICP. I like to think of it as an
audience of one. So like if there was
just one person in a chair in front of
you that's like probably somebody in the
lab. You can just picture them right
now. It's like if I could give value on
every single piece of content to that
person, there's a lot more people like
that and it would scale accordingly. The
algorithms in the last like one to two
years have gotten so good at targeting
the exact type of person you want that
you don't actually need more than like
10 to 20,000 views per post on Instagram
other than for ego reasons. You can
drive a ton of email lead genen from
that. So I would say like the first
thing is narrow is good. You can there's
things we can talk about in terms of how
to expand the saturation within that
narrow slice like the way you frame the
hooks and the topics but like you want
narrow. If our ICP are other creators
who are educational in nature for their
audiences,
my perspective has been that education
has been harder to do well on uh
especially Instagram and Tik Tok. But
that might be a limiting belief too when
you see people who are doing education
in short form video and doing it well.
What is true about those folks that
they're being successful in a world
where there's a lot of just like great
pure entertainment that is probably more
engaging?
>> Yeah. How do you define doing it well?
Are you talking about views?
>> That's a good question. I would say
doing it well in terms of uh they are
making Instagram worthwhile for them.
[laughter] Guess is like the ultimate
answer. I would say that probably in the
back of my mind when I asked that
question was like okay yes they're
they're doing good views. They're doing
views on par with people who aren't
doing education. You know the target
market for this is actually fairly
large. So if if views are in the
singledigit thousands, it feels like
there's just a lot being left on the
table. So views as a metric doesn't
matter in an absolute sense, but it
feels like we are really barely
scratching the surface
>> 100%. So I would say views are not the
right metric to study. Views are a
metric to study and I would say the
third most important when I look at the
stack. I also think not all views are
created equal, right? So an
entertainment video that has a million
views is not getting the trust
accumulation the same way an education
video it's 40,000 views. It's super
dense. So that that does make it hard.
The hard part is this decoupling from
like the thing you can see from other
people which is views and your own like
all of our brains are like see number
num want number bigger compare number
right and so it can cause a lot of
people to stop or to go down the wrong
path when they're anchoring views as the
number one metric. And here here's what
I mean by that. If you know professional
creators are the number one target
audience and you know all you have to do
is get them to trust you and they will
ascend down the funnel because you have
all that dialed. You just got to get
their email and you know that you can
monetize them. If you know that's true
and you know that education content is
the best way to get trust at scale.
Let's just hold those things constant.
Then you studying an entertainment video
from someone else is actually
distracting you from like the right
benchmark. Right? the right benchmark is
am I making a a high trust high value
video educationally to get one more
content minute on the stack like in a
vacuum right looking me looking at Logan
Paul does nothing for me right me
looking at I'm just thinking of like
random entertainment names and so the
number one thing I think to to go
through is what what are the best
metrics to track and maybe I could just
share like how I'm approaching this on
my channels cuz I basically solve short
form in like a pseudo entertainment
niche you could say like I was doing
tech, which sounds educational, but
really it's like entertainment. And I
was doing that for a brand deal
strategy. So like that was a game to
play. The game you're playing and the
game I'm now playing on my Callway
marketing, completely different game.
And so even me, like I can't really look
at tech as a proxy for marketing because
it's completely different. So maybe I
can explain like what I'm doing on
Callaway Marketing and how I'm looking
at it.
>> The three metrics that I think matter
most, number one is conversions per
video. And conversions measured as
emails collected per video. That means
every video I have a CTA. Every CTA is
driving to a lead magnet where I can
capture emails and I'm measuring all of
those in many chat and I can go through
like this batch process that I run.
That's number one. Number two is
followers gained per video. That is more
valuable than views because a follow
when someone goes to follow it's like
five to 10x more powerful because
they're like that was so good I can't
miss it again. So before I looked at
total views I would look at followers
gained and just say which one is driving
more followers. Last I would look at
total views. Now, the reason why total
views is helpful when you're looking at
competition is because you don't you
don't have insight really into how many
email subscribers their videos are
driving or how many followers gain.
Those are like private metrics behind
the wall. But you could look at someone
else's and see views. So, if you're
looking at like what's working for
others, you have to settle for views for
others cuz you can't see the other two.
Something I admire about Callaway is his
willingness to invest in experts to help
him skip the learning curve. That's what
he did when he hired the one of 10 team
to help with his YouTube channel. You
probably know the one of 10 team as the
leading tool for researching viral
ideas, titles, and thumbnails. It's what
I use the most on my channel. The reason
the tool works so well is that the team
is full of YouTube strategists who
really know their stuff. What you may
not know is that they also have a
consulting arm that's not only worked
with Callaway, but Olly Abdal, Will
Tennyson, Mike Shake, and a bunch of
others, too. Collectively, they've
helped generate over 2 billion views for
their clients. The one of 10 team helped
Callaway grow a new channel from zero to
over 250,000 subscribers in just one
year. They helped with this video, this
video, and this video, too. One video
alone brought in over 2 million views
and generated more than $100,000 in
revenue. If you want to work with the
same team that took Callaway from zero
subscribers to where he is now, that's
the one of 10 strategy team. They are
very selective with who they work with
and only take on about five new clients
per month. They focus on the things that
actually move the needle, ideas, titles,
thumbnails, and positioning. You get a
dedicated Slack channel and regular
one-on-one calls to communicate with
their team to ensure each video is set
up for success. This is not a course,
and it's not a one-time solution. It's
[music] direct ongoing support from a
real YouTube expert who has done this
for some of YouTube's largest creators.
[music]
book a free discovery call with the one
of 10 team today with the link in the
description and let them know that Jay
sent you. But when you look at your own
channel, the biggest trap I find is only
relying on views from your own channel
because obviously if the TAM is bigger
on a topic, you're going to get more
views. And so if you expand the TAM
beyond the trust zone, those views are
actually empty calories. And so that's
like just one anchoring methodology that
I think about is can we have enough lead
magnets in the ecosystem that we can
drive to a lead magnet on every video
and then evaluate emails collected per
video. So I the Callaway marketing
channel I've been running for I think
I'm 35 videos in and the goal is to get
to 2x per day. We're doing one per day,
seven per week right now. Every single
one of them I have a CTA. Every single
one of them I'm measuring. And what's
funny is not always are the highest view
ones driving the most emails, which
which is like you would you would
probably accept that to be true and same
as me, but the average person would be
like, "Wa, I'd expect views equal
emails." It's not the case, right? It's
all about what's acrewing trust, what's
what's targeting a painoint people
really have a need for, and then you
have a lead magnet complimenting.
>> So, when you're doing these CTAs with
these lead magnets, are you reverse
engineering a video topic based on a
lead magnet you made? Do you have an
idea for a video you love and then you
create a lead magnet for that and now
that's just in the bank and maybe we'll
use it again when it makes sense in the
future. What's your order of operations?
>> Yeah, so I've done it both ways. So I
have an academy where I like teach my
whole system to people and what I've
done is I've taken pieces of the
academy, extracted them out and turned
it into a lead magnet. So then I'm just
like I have that lead magnet made. If
the topic suits it, I'll pull from it.
So I guess like step one is you have a
couple that you believe in. Right now,
when if I were going to like what videos
do you make, I wouldn't make them based
on the lead magnet. I would make them
based on what I can talk about next,
which is like how you actually identify
which topics are working. I would say
it's probably maybe we can get into this
now in terms of like topics because one
of the questions you asked is like
what's the most important thing to to to
look for to to focus on? By far and
away, it's the idea of the video. Like
you can use almost any hook, any
storytelling structure, any editing, any
format. If you have a bad topic, and I
can talk about what bad and good looks
like, the video will fail. it'll it'll
be medium at best, but if you have a
great topic, you can plug in almost any
of those other things and it will almost
always work. So all like the 8020 9010
is can I pick topics that are validated,
relevant to pain points they want and
that I have a non-obvious contrarian
take about. So for me like if I had a
pie chart of where topics come from, I
would say like at the beginning 70 to
80% comes from data for what other
creators topically have talked about
that have worked. and I'm looking at
views because that's all I have access
to. And so I'm informing my first couple
batches of content based on that 20%
comes one out of every five comes from
like an original idea where I'm just
like let's just test this. That first
couple batches and I do batches of 10.
So let's say like 20 to 30 videos is all
about testing. I'm basically just trying
to validate which topics work best for
me. Once I then know that we we could
talk about like downstream, but you know
topics are the most important thing. And
what I'll do is based on the topic that
I choose, I'll then plug in whatever the
closest lead magnet would be to that
topic. The way I think of it is I don't
really want to spend every hour making
content. Like I'd rather live my life,
right? And so I'm trying to like
increase I'm trying to derisk my effort
slash increase my hit rate. So every
time I sit down, I want it to bang so
that I get the result so I don't have to
spend more hours doing it. That's kind
of like how I think of it. So it's the
measure twice, cut once. Like what would
be the way to derisk? The way to derisk
is to use data on the topics and then
creativity on the contrarian insights.
That combo is like that's what all the
goat creators are doing. I mean on I
would say on YouTube and that's what I
do on YouTube too on YouTube and short
form. Uh and it makes it so much easier
and that that's basically why I built
sand castles, right? So like for anyone
who knows Sandcastle.ai that's like my
software tool AI tool that does a lot of
this for me. The reason why I built that
is because I went data first from the
beginning because I really did not enjoy
the process of spending 10 hours on a
video and it failing. I like hated that
a lot. So I was which I'm sure everyone
does obviously but I was like I can't do
this forever. Like I can't do the
guessing. So I was like how do I use
data but not make myself a clone that's
copy pasting everyone else's stuff
because I also think that's where you
lose too. If you're a derivative you're
going to lose. So you have to be
original but you have to fish in the
right ponds. That's that's the key
thing. If you're fishing in every pond,
some ponds don't have fish. So, it's
like, how do we figure out where to fish
and then use our own technique, our own
contrarian insight, our own, you know,
whatever the metaphor, our own boat to
go get more fish, right? So, the way I
do it with sand castles, which I think
is the best way right now is,
>> can you show us this?
>> So, this is sand castles in the upper
left, you can build like separate
workspaces for different niches. So,
like you might want to say, okay,
professional creators is like my main
one, but you might have other like
verticals you want to test if you want
to if you want to partition them
separately, right? So, this is my
marketing workspace. Basically, the
first thing you want to do is build this
channel list. So, if you go to the
channels tab, I've got this list here of
like all the top creators that I've come
across or that I know of in my category.
And like you, like I said, you can
either build this one time or like over
time. But how you would do it is maybe
let's just delete all of these so I can
show you uh kind of the process from
scratch. So, typically you would come in
here and you'd be like, I don't know who
to add at all. So you go to describe and
let's just say you're looking for like
for me social media marketing and growth
content and I can say I only want people
from Instagram or I only want people
from micro and small cat which is like
10k followers to 250k. Now I'll go up to
medium. The reason you want this micro
to medium range is because typically,
and this is like not intuitive, but if
you track videos from massive people
like Horosi, let's say, who has like
four or five million followers,
typically when he has an outlier, it's
not necessarily just because the idea
did so well. It's because he's so famous
and has so much uh built-in like brand
equity that people will like anything he
does. So, it's actually a counter signal
to study the huge people. You just won't
find the best ideas. Conversely, let's
say you're not wellknown at all. If you
have a banger, that means the idea, the
concept, the substance was the reason
why. It's not because of your face
because nobody knows you, right? So, you
want to study people that are slightly
smaller in the that's where really the
golden ideas come from. So, let's just
do like these three and we'll press
search. So, what Sand Castle does is it
breaks whatever you gave it into three
different buckets. So, in this case,
social media marketing, social media
growth, marketing and growth strategies,
like they're all kind of derivatives of
this. And this will give you the best
ranked channels that we have on our in
our database. We have like 100,000
channels or so. And if you want to see
more, you can just load more. And the
goal is you just highlight that or you
you you hover over these. And you if you
want to investigate these, you can just
click and open it in a new tab. Boom.
This person's in a new tab. I don't know
if it's sh it's probably not sharing,
but like I open it. Boom. I see her
channel. Here it is. And what you want
to do is build out your list. So I could
say like social with Philip. Boom. Press
the plus and I build him out here. Now
you can do this quickly by just pressing
add all. And what we do in the
onboarding is like automatically build a
list of 20 for you. But I find like most
people want to tailor this pretty
tightly. Now the cool the cool thing
about a few like hidden features we have
here is like let's say so uh Jaden is
really dope. Like he's dope in the
space. I've seen his stuff. So like I'm
I'm going to add him. Now what's cool is
I can hit this little double arrows
here. And what we'll do is make him the
anchor. And now these are all the best
fits based on like closest to him. So if
you let's say you're not good at
describing what you want to do, but you
f you know there's one anchor person
that you love, you can just go to him,
press this, boom, now this list is like
the closest possible thing to him. So I
would just like add all these people in.
Right? So that's how that's one way to
do it. The other way is if you know
someone's good, like this girl Ava is
really good in the space. I'll just
search her name, personal brand launch,
and if you just wait a second, it will
find her. So she's right here. Now, like
I said, we only have 100,000 channels.
like these are top curated channels and
our users every time a user adds one it
gets added to the database. But if
there's somebody that exists that you
know should be there and they're not, it
just means nobody has ever added them to
Sandcastle. So you can actually do it
for free. You just go to add URL and you
can type it in. So we have this. I'll go
to parse. If we have you, the picture
shows up. Boom. I add you. No problem.
If we didn't have you, it would be like
new channel and you can import it. And
then when you import it, we'll take in
your full backlog, right? And so th this
process of building out your list is
super valuable because now you can focus
your attention, you can focus your
research attention on these channels
which you know to be good. So what I
recommend for people is like almost
everybody knows at least one name of
someone that's pretty pretty good in
their niche. Start with that person,
search them or add them and then just go
to this kind of refactor. And then once
you hit this refactor, you can just be
like, "Okay, boom. These are all the
people that are really close to this
person." So we'll add a bunch in there.
One thing that's interesting about this
approach that's a little bit counter to
like the YouTube advice in a similar
fashion is a lot of times the advice on
YouTube is like get outside your niche.
Find somebody who's doing something in
finance or gaming that's interesting and
try to pull from their video ideas which
I think makes sense but I don't know it
doesn't seem like it would translate
exactly to Instagram but I having a hard
time articulating why that's true.
>> Yeah. So I think there's there's like
different buckets right. So when you do
the YouTube research, if you're looking
for topic inspiration or interest topics
on YouTube, you need to have people that
are in your space or like very close
adjacent. But if you're looking for
title formats or thumbnail inspiration
or series ideas, you can go broader,
right? For example, if you were doing
creator stuff, you typically wouldn't
look in the ecom niche for like interest
topics, but you could find a title
format that's crushing and then
translate it over. It's kind of similar
here where if you're looking for topics,
you need the topics to be within niche.
But if you want to look for formats or
you want to look at editing styles or
you want to look at hook hook, you know,
hook formats, you could do that outside
the niche as well. So what we found is
like most people have trouble building a
list outside of their core niche. Like
most people are not aware of like who's
good, what's good, even like this
databacked process. So we try to keep it
in niche and then you can I'll show you
a couple things we have where you can
stumble across new stuff that's like
outside the niche. But this is this is
what I like to start with. So this is my
list. You can see I just I had a list on
Excel. I just pasted all the URLs in. I
added them super quick. So this is the
list that like I I like. So once you
have this, then you go to the videos
tab. And so this is the to to zoom out.
What we're doing here is we're breaking
down how do you find the best performing
topics in your niche so that you know
which ponds to fish in. So if you go to
the videos tab, what you now see are
these are all the videos from just those
channels. And you know that because if
you click the channels filter, you can
see the channels in here. So, if I
wanted to look at like just my channel,
I would click my channel and then I've
got boom, I got all the videos from just
my channel in here. Now, the difference
between this and like Instagram or Tik
Tok proper is that I can filter and cut
this data however I want. So, what I
like to do is I'll go posted in the last
two months. I like to set engagement
rate at 2% because that filters out the
brand deals. Typically, if you have
videos with super high views, but they
have 0% engagement, it's because people
paid to boost the views. I don't want to
look at the brand deals because those
are that give me a that gives me a false
sense of what topics worked. So I just
set this bottom engagement at 2%.
Anything below that filters out. And
then what I do is I go to sort and I'll
go either outlier score or views.
Slightly different ways of calculating
it, but let's just do outlier score. So
the outlier score, which is this green
badge here, you can see like this one is
8.2x. This means that the views of this
video were 8.2x 2x higher or above the
average views in the rolling 3 months
before this video was posted. We do
rolling three months so that if the
channel's dying, the outlier score kind
of gets recalculated. You don't get
punished for like super fast or super
slow growth. But so an outlier score is
like a better apples to apples
comparison across multiple channels. So
the beauty of this is like let's say I
clear uh just this and I look at the
whole cohort. Now, this is in the last 2
months sorted by outlier score across
all these channels, the top performing
videos. So, like this is the the wise
investor. I don't even know maybe that
maybe he's on the channel, but there's
Ganon, uh, Peter Visuals, etc. So, you
go through. So, now what you can do,
there's a few things that are like super
helpful. Let me let me go by newest so I
can show you this. When you see these
videos, the very first thing you're
you're probably wanting to do is either
play it in a new tab, so you can just
watch it. So you can just hover over and
play a new tab like this. Or you want to
get deep analysis on this video, like
what is the transcript? How can I
understand like what this video was
about? Right? And so if you just press
this analyze button, we will actually do
a deep analysis on this video. And if
I'll just go back to one that I've
already analyzed.
So like this one by Ganon, I can press
into it. You get the transcript, the
caption if you wanted is here. But then
all this like deep analysis, right? So
what is the topic? What was the the seed
of the idea? The topic is like a 3 to
five word kind of description. This is
more like a single sentence description.
What is the unique angle of this video?
What is the common belief versus
contrarian reality? This is like really
where curiosity comes from right here.
What kind of like core facts or evidence
did he put in this video? Then we go to
the hook. What was the formula for the
hook? What was the exact hook? What was
the analysis of why this hooked work?
What is the category of the hook?
Storytelling, same thing. Category, what
what the storytelling structure was?
Visuals as well. So the whole point is
like now you're getting all of the deep
analysis on this video. We're both
taking the transcript and literally
watching it with a vision model and
giving you insights on this. Now at an
individual level, you could be like,
"Oh, cool." Like I'm just going to A lot
of people just use sand castles like
this. They come in, they filter, they
sort by outlier score, and literally
they just watch each one. They're just
like, "Watch, watch, watch." And and
they like watching it themselves. They
don't even want the detailed analysis.
This alone prevents you from having to
scroll to find ideas and now you can see
the best performers. I'll I'll expand on
what I would look what I would take from
this verse not to keep it original, but
like that's that's like the lightest
weight way to do it. The more advanced
way is once you analyze a bunch of these
and you can go one at a time or you can
press bulk analyze like you know let's
say you wanted to analyze my channel.
You would just search my channel. You
could say bulk analyze 50 videos or you
know you could look and say okay that
looks like there's 25 in the last three
weeks. I'm just going to bulk analyze
25. Once you have all these analyzed you
can either export the data as a CSV and
feed that into Claude or you can use our
MCP which connects Sand Castles directly
to Claude. You can just install it in
like 30 seconds. I can I can link a
video if people want. And then in Claude
I can say look at the last 30 videos
from Callaway Marketing's channel. Make
sure they're all deep analyzed. give me
a full report of like a breakdown of the
topics, the hooks, etc. Right? So,
there's so much you can do with this
data individually and as a cohort.
>> So, you're coming in here for Callaway
Marketing and you're doing your uh your
filtering, your sorting, you have a
short list by outlier score. When do you
stop and say like, "Yep, that's one I'm
going to do." Is it something that like
inspiration hits or are you doing a
minimum 10 and then saying, "Okay, which
one of these did did I feel best?"
What's your process from here? So
there's so there's two paths. There's
looking at what competitors are doing to
get new ideas and then there's looking
at your own channel to understand all
the other stuff that's working really
well. So like which videos did I make
that crushed? What hooks are working?
What formats are working, right? So I I
kind of like do both separately, per se.
So I've got a guy on my team um that
literally just does the idea stuff all
day long. So, he's looking at all of
these competitor channels and he's like
trying to like he looks at this this
view right here and sometimes he'll go
uh last, you know, 30 days. Sometimes
he'll go further out. It depends on like
for your niche and my niche. This is
pretty evergreen. So, you can go back
like four four six months and still get
good ideas. For newsbased niches where
you need more like real-time stuff,
he'll do 14 days or seven days like for
tech. So, he'll look at this and he'll
open this video and he'll be like,
"Okay, is the topic of this interesting
to him?" First of all, like because I've
kind of trained him on like what
interesting looks like just like are you
curious about this period? Okay. Number
two, do we have something relevant and
non-obvious to say about this general
topic? So, like let's just look at this
one right here. So, we'll open this. So,
let's just watch this.
This video got nearly 25 million views.
[music] That's over 200 times more views
than the creator's regular content. And
the reason comes down to one thing. Your
brain is always trying to guess what
happens [music] next in a So this is
basically like a a hook case study where
he's explaining the hook or psychology
of this, right? So my my guy or you or
anyone who's doing this, right, would be
like, okay, this is a breakdown of an
example video that had a viral hook that
had traction that he explained how to do
it. So, the close clone, which I don't
really like doing close clones, would be
like, let's take this exact same video
and make a like this exact same example
and make our own spin on it where we
break down the hook, but in a different
way. We say different stuff. To me,
that's still too close. I want to be
more unique. So, I would say, okay,
interesting. The style that he went
through to explain this is he started
with the hook itself of of the example.
He played it without saying anything.
Then, he introduced what it was and
broke it down. Could we run a similar
flow like that, a similar story
structure, but using a different
example? Do we have a different example?
Do I have unique insights to say on a
different example? That would like start
the process. So, if if my uh my like
head of content pulled this and he he
thought we would have something good, he
would put it in the list for us to
review. If he thought it was like too
junk foody, he would pass, right? But
the reason why like that's helpful is
all these are on target and they're the
best performers by the people in my
niche. So it just focuses your yes no
process super dialed. So he'll do this
uh daily or every other day and he
builds a Google doc that has tabs on the
side and every tab is like a separate
idea. He's only putting the ones on
there that he thinks we have something
good to say, right? And it's based on
the whole corp like I've just trained
him over time like the whole corpus of
everything I believe. He's seen all my
YouTube videos. He knows kind of like
our isms, let's say. Then we get on a
call. I like to do it twice a week where
he'll pitch me each one and be like,
"Here's what I found. This crushed.
Here's what I think we could do. What do
you think?" If I don't have something
unique to say that's like contrarian and
interesting, we kill it. If I do have
something unique to say and I'm like,
"Ooh, that's cool. We should use this
other video as the example." Or, "Ooh,
we could bring in this one framework
that I talk about and like, you know,
I'll I'll construct it." We we green
light it and we put it into like
approved bucket. We'll go through that
call like we just did one today for an
hour or so. And what that gives us is
like eight to 10 approved ideas where
they're validated by data. I know we
have something interesting. We went back
and forth for five minutes on the call
for each idea and like kind of
brainstorm the best option. And then
from there I know I can go into the
scripting phase. So that's kind of like
the research flow. Now he's most for
short form mostly he's using sand
castles. Like he doesn't really scroll
that much. Uh for YouTube he's looking
at uh or like for for tech ideas he's
looking at Twitter and other other
things like that like email newsletters
around tech. But for like Callaway
marketing, the marketing ideas, he's
pretty much just looking at this. So
that's the how do we get new ideas just
on the topic front.
>> How are people doing this before they
there was a tool like this? Were they
just like
>> manually?
>> Manually with like uh bookmarks and
folders
>> and spending a lot of time on their
phone.
>> Yeah. like they either had a person like
a social media strategist or them and
they were scrolling for like two to
three hours a day and they were having
to go through all the noise, all the
nonsense is not on target and then
they'd have to see all the ones that are
like mid- performers. Then finally
they'd get to some bangers and the ratio
from my research was like one out of 10
or one out of 20 would be like even
close to potentially relevant and then
you'd have to see it. You'd you'd
bookmark it or you'd save the link into
a notes file. You'd have a bunch and
then you'd go through this process of
like is it relevant? Is it not? So, this
just speeds up a lot of the research
time. So, you don't have to spend all
that time doing the the finding. Right
now, we also have like this automations
feature, which I think is pretty sick.
You can set up these rules that will
automatically deep analyze whichever
videos you want based on the conditions.
Right? So, what I'll do is we have this
one on that says for any of the channels
in our list, as long as there's a 5x
outlier score on the video and it has
above 2% engagement, we want you to
autoprocess it. So it'll automatically
be analyzed. And what that means is when
it's analyzed, it's ready to be pulled
from in Claude, right? Because we have
the MCP set up. So we could just set up
a daily scrape that's like, give me the
best performing videos of the day today,
every day. And we could set that up as a
scheduled task. It can do that. I mean,
it could it could just give you the
video to like link out without analyzing
it. But by analyzing it, we can also
have it say, "What are the common topics
that are working?" And it can just know
because it's already done all this
analysis for you automatically. So, this
is just like one way to speed it up cuz
you you can tell like my whole thing is
like how do we speed this up as fast as
possible and get as much signal as we
can in the workflow.
>> This clearly solves my topic ideation
and even to a degree hook problem
because I can see how this is working.
The next place where I feel like I would
fall down is if the video is too long or
in some way like the structure of the
whole video goes off the rails. Is the
answer to just use this analyze feature
and look at the structure of these and
make sure I'm following fairly closely
to it and then just be relentless in the
edit.
>> Yeah. So, there's two ways. So, when
you're when you're first starting and
you don't have a ton of your own data,
like you don't have a ton of your own
videos, the best way would be find a
creator that you like, like let's say
Ganon, find the a creator where you like
the flow of. It's not like you like the
look of his stuff cuz that's the
visuals. It's more like you like the way
he explains stuff, you like the flow of
his storytelling. You can use this
transcript and you can either look just
look at it and be like, "Okay, roughly
speaking, these are the sections." We
also have a feature right here that's
show sections. You just press this. So,
it breaks it down into like the five
parts or they're not always five, but
this in this case there's five parts.
So, you could then say, "Okay, cool."
Like, if I'm going to storytell, but I
don't want to I don't want to copy his
stuff. We need a hook. We need an intro
to the series. Then, in this case, he's
doing a setup tutorial. There's a live
demo and a payoff. So, like at the at
the roughest strokes, you could copy
that structure. At the most detailed
strokes, you could take his exact script
and then try to translate it into your
own. Now, you could do this manually or
of course you can take a hundred scripts
from Ganon, put it into Claude and be
like, I want to understand what the best
performing structures are storytelling
wise from the scripts. Make me a skill
file template and then when I jump in a
topic, write a script for me in that
way. Now, I likely would not just just
go with that. Like, I would take that
and then I'd tweak it. That's going to
be 90% of the way there. But that gets
you again like it puts guard rails on
what you should do when you don't know
what I recommend doing once you have a
minimum amount of videos for yourself
like 10 to 20 videos you know let's go
to mine I have all of my videos analyzed
so of course I can look one by one like
if I sort by outlier score my eye is
trained on content now where I can see
like let me go 60 days so we have all of
them in there I can see like okay this
was about kind of content strategy this
was about AI tools this was about
storytelling this was about formats This
is about strategy. Strategy. This one I
think is storytelling. Storytelling. So
I'm starting to see like common buckets
like I can just look at it and see. But
on the on the story structure side, the
storytelling like with the script, you
could just take these and once they're
analyzed, you can again like export the
data or use claude and just say, "Hey,
I've made 20 videos. Can you look at the
top the top five performers and just
help me understand like what is the
common structure or flow of the script
that's working well for me? let's turn
that into a template or turn that into a
skill file and then when I feed you a
new topic, can you write the script or
at least guide me into what those
buckets should be? To your point, like
that'll that'll speed up a lot of the
confusion. I still think you need like
writing is the number one creative tool.
Like I believe writing is the most
important skill. I think you believe
that as well. So I never want to like
fully outsource every word I say to
this, but like as a as a 75 85 90% of
the way their first draft automatic,
it's pretty sick. And then you can tweak
from there. Yeah, I agree. Um the the
conflicting feelings that I get when I
think about processes like this is if
you remove all of your own creative work
and writing from it, which you totally
could. Like I could make this totally
data driven and totally like automated
formula
>> from this and it would probably get
results and I just know that would be
like not satisfying for me either. Like
what I like about these this analyze
tools and these headers that you have in
this transcript, I can teach myself to
fish with this tool. I don't have to let
the tool fish for me.
>> Exactly. The way I like to think of it
is so in in the content workflow, you've
got topic, you've got research or like
substance, you've got hook, script,
record, edit, post. In each of those
little little modules within the flow,
you can decide to turn it all the way to
100 on data or all the way to zero on
manual. and you can pick where you want.
So like for me, where I'm at right now
is I really like using 100% data to
guide me on the topic buckets so that I
know where to start fishing. Then I look
at my own my own data. Like the most
valuable thing like just on YouTube, the
most valuable data for you on YouTube is
your own channel. Same thing here. But
until you have your own data, you just
guiding on the topics that make the most
sense from other people is the best way
to do it. For substance, the contrarian
insight, I'm relying on my creativity.
I'm not really like taking other
people's insights cuz I find that's
really like the sauce that makes it
unique and that's the creative challenge
for me is like okay how do I take this
30 days of content topic and make it
unique. So I came up with this new
mechanism and like that did pretty well.
So on the substance I'm doing it full
creativity on the hooks and the
scripting. What exactly what you said is
where I'm at which is like the goal is
to make your brain full of what works so
that when you flow naturally creatively
it's already infused in there, right? So
like you just when I look at this I'm
like okay let me study right here. Let
me study what this is. When I make
another one I don't copy paste it. I
just read it just like copy work or like
any form of training yourself on a
skill. I'm reading it and I'm like, "Oh,
okay. I see like how that flowed and
that didn't. Okay, now I know." So, when
I go to write from scratch, it's kind of
like in my brain already. The way of
doing this, that's the like most manual
way to use data, but still be fully
creative. You can of course dial that a
little bit more where it's like, cool,
I'm going to start copy pasting this one
that worked. It's my own words, but like
I'm going to start here and then edit
around it. The the full automated would
be like literally just rip this and
change a couple words. So to your point,
you can season to taste on this
depending on how much creative
expression you want. I don't think you
can fully build an AI factory pumping it
out with zero creativity and cut
through. I just think there's too much
supply and it's going to trend towards
average because most people are doing
that and they're coming up with the same
stuff. So this is where like I call it
data enabled creativity. That's my like
big theme or thesis that I believe in is
like using the data to guide you and
then allowing basically freeing up all
of your time to be creative and using
data for everything else. What if I took
one of your uh one of these videos that
we're looking at on screen right now and
I removed all visuals? The cut stayed
there, but it was just you and it was
just captions. How big of an impact do
you think that would make on the
performance of that video?
>> A pure yap with zero graphics, which is
kind of what you're describing, right?
like full A-roll U and captions ba
basically the way I the the framework I
use to look at this is like a picture is
worth a thousand words right so if you
have no visuals on the screen you're
relying on the viewer's imagination to
to come up with if they're a visual
learner like I am they have to imagine
what you're saying and try to get
comprehension from that more technical
or the more complex or the more like out
there ideas you're talking about the
harder it is for people to imagine it's
a spectrum right it's like the more work
you the more frontend effort you apply
to the production, the le the the easier
it is to carve a moat visually because
there's just less people putting in that
time. However, to your point, the more
resource intensive it is. So, you have
to just experiment along that spectrum
and figure out what you are happy with
and then ultimately what converts into
emails. That's that's a really critical
thing too.
>> Amazing. Well, I will link sand castles
in the description for this. That's
fantastic.
>> If you're a business owner, hopefully
this is helpful to you. Definitely free
stuff below, so feel free to check it
out. Now that you've seen exactly how
Callaway structures his content
research, you'll love seeing behind the
scenes with Riley Brown, too.